all right
[Music]
previously I've explored how tongue
cleaning may be the best way to cut down
on bad breath and have the remarkable
side benefit of potentially helping with
blood pressure regulation as Daily
Tongue cleaning appears to favor The
increased abundance metabolic activity
of the good bacteria on your tongue that
help you make your body's natural artery
dilator nitric oxide but there's another
way tongue cleaning May improve your
blood pressure
after two weeks of tongue cleaning you
can improve your sensitivity to tasting
salt and a follow-up study found that
just a single cleaning can do it they
applied a drop of tomato soup to
people's tongues before and after they
cleaned their tongues with a plastic
tongue scraper with the adorable name
scrapey
and they experienced a significant
increase in salt taste intensity why is
that good because of a simple tongue
cleaning could change the perceived
intensity of salt it could be used to
rapidly make lower salt concentrations
more acceptable to people without
changing the palatability of the food
they therefore recommend that people
scrape their tongue every day in order
to adapt to foods with lower salt
concentrations to effectively decrease
their taste for death
after all excess sodium intake is the
deadliest thing about the human diet
responsible for millions of deaths every
year so that benefit alone could justify
tongue cleaning
okay so what's the best way to do it a
systematic review of meta-analysis
include that tongue cleaning offers
benefits however there's insufficient
evidence to recommend a specific
frequency duration or method of tongue
cleaning but let's see what data are out
there tongue scraping was found to be
slightly more effective than tongue
brushing and treating bad breath perhaps
due to the fact that the width of a
toothbrush is smaller than the width of
a tongue scraper but there are now
toothbrushes on the market with a tongue
Scraper on the back of their head here's
what they look like and they seem to
have a similar performance in terms of
breath Improvement
some people feel that tongue brushing is
more gag inducing than tongue scraping
so appear to prefer scrapers on the
other hand if you just brush your tongue
you don't have to buy an extra Gizmo
technique wise you want to make sure you
include the back of your tongue and
importantly the cleaning should be
gentle to prevent damaging your tongue
cleaning too hard with a tongue scraper
can risk tongue injury and you should
just clean the top surface of your
tongue not the sides of your tongue how
often should you do it tooth brushing
should be twice a day but the tongue
cleaning recommendation seem to be more
uncertain so researchers decide to study
the rate of reformation of tongue
Coatings after scraping they took folks
who had at least 20 percent of their
tongue covered with a coating thick
enough to conceal the pink color of
their tongue they started out with about
a third of their tongue covered and
scraping reduced it to under 10 the
question is how long would it take to
regrow on average tongue coating scores
had returned to Baseline levels on day
two so if tongue clean needs to be
recommended it should probably be
performed on a daily basis
what kind of scraper is best researchers
had people try nine different tongue
scrapers here are the brand names rated
using six different criteria and these
two were most preferred out of the
available options
what's the best way to disinfect tongue
scrapers and toothbrushes in my video on
the best water purifier I ended up
speaking about disinfecting your
toothbrush by soaking it in a 50 50
white vinegar water solution for 10
minutes but this is even easier just
microwaving your toothbrush or tongue
scraper for one minute then you don't
have to keep buying new toothbrushes and
it's interesting we don't even know
exactly why it works like you think it's
just heat sterilization but there must
be other factors since I nuked my
toothbrush for a minute and hardly even
got warm but it
kills off the bacteria nonetheless
what about all the fancy new tongue
cleaners on the market throughout the
last century there have been many U.S
Pattinson various ingenious tongue
cleaning devices I mean how much money
can you make selling plain little cheap
plastic one so how about an ultrasound
Tongue Cleaner or tongue cleaning using
a high-speed vacuum ejector or a suction
tongue cleaning device like a like a
tongue Roomba but alas a consensus group
of dental professionals say there's no
evidence that substantiates the benefits
of using any kind of electrical device
to clean your tongue in fact the lowest
Tech option is in everyone's home right
now without buying a thing you can just
use a simple spoon
[Music]
thank you